So, Tom, this is the moment.
It's one of the great set piece moments, not just in French history, but in all European history, isn't it?
The humiliation of the king and queen by this group, either, as you would say, of tender hearted representatives of the people or slavering beasts from the slums and sewers, depending, of course, on the way you view it.
You frame it.
So the baker, Mrs. Baker, and the baker's boy, they're the king, the queen, and the dauphin, who's what, five, something like that?
Yeah, something like that.
Very young.
So they effectively, from this point onwards, if they weren't already, they are prisoners of the revolution, held in captivity.
And you could argue this is the great turning point in the story of the revolution?
I think certainly for the king and queen, it's a much more significant turning point.
And it's clearly a massive turning point in the history of the revolution.
But you could equally argue that it is kind of drawing a line under a whole series of measures and developments that have been happening over the previous months.
It's a kind of logical conclusion to what's been happening.
So just to remind listeners of what those developments are.
The Bastille stormed on the 14th of July, and then that August of 1789.
And you have the revocation of feudal privileges, where all the aristocrats and abbots and people stand up and renounce all their various perks.
And that's passed on the 11th of August.
And then on the 26th of August, their approval is given in the National Assembly for the Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen, which is what we were talking about in yesterday's episode.
But what we kind of briefly touched on, but didn't really explore, is the way that the...
The Declaration of the Rights of Man.
I mean, just on the ideological level, it raises as many questions as it answers.
And there are definitely those in the National Assembly, but also more broadly in Paris, who feel it does not go far enough.
So what we didn't talk about yesterday, which I'm sure lots of our particularly female listeners will have been wondering, is what about the rights of women and the citizeness?
And that is a topic that we'll be looking...
We'll be looking at later.
Essentially, there is quite, I think, a kind of misogynist tone to revolutionary zeal.
Well, all the stuff about virtue and virility has been laying the ground for that, right?
They always talk about the oath of the Horatii, the great Romans, but they're always talking about men, never about women.
Yes.
And although women do play a key part in this story, they tend to be a kind of anonymous mass.
That is how they're celebrated, not as individuals.
Also, the other kind of burning question, then as now, what about slaves?
The French own huge plantations in the Caribbean.
They say liberty for all, but equally they say property rights must be respected.
So there is an unresolved tension there, again, that we might explore in due course.
But of course, more immediately for the future of France and its constitution.
What about the monarchy?
Because how is the role of the king to be squared with the declaration and with the ideals of the revolution?
So yesterday we were looking at the church, but I mean, in a way, the king is an even bigger roadblock to that idea of a single nation, a single patrie.
Because as we were saying before, a lot of these revolutions are inspired by Montesquieu's ideas about a sort of a mixed constitution, a separation of powers.
And the idea of the British constitutional monarchy as a model.
So something like the Comte de Mirabeau, who we've talked about, a great sort of figure in the assembly at this point.
He's all about a British style monarchy, isn't he?
And they need somebody to play that part.
What they're not talking about at this point is a republican democracy.
So they need, they want to have a king shaped whole and they want a king, a patriot king to fill it.
They do.
So Mirabeau is, you know, I mean, he's a hero of the revolution.
He's seen as a great patriot.
But he is allying himself with kind of nobles who are less motivated by revolutionary fervor.
So they, I mean, they are literally a metropolitan elite.
These are nobles from Paris who are very rich, very highly educated, and who are fascinated by the British example.
So Anglomanie, the fascination with England as a model, has been a trend running throughout the 18th century, even as France has been at war with Britain.
And so.
So Mirabeau and these kind of metropolitan nobles are proposing in the national assemblies, they've got a kind of constitutional committee set up to ponder these issues.
They're saying that we should model our constitution on British practice.
And although they are very, very careful to point out that they will, their version will be better than the British one, because they will learn from the British example.
No such version exists, even in theory.
You might think that.
So what they're proposing is.
An elected national assembly, which would correspond to the House of Commons, a Senate, which would be drawn from the great and the good, and obviously is corresponds to the House of Lords and this Senate initially they wanted to be for life.
And then there are kind of objections to this.
And so they say, well, you know, it could, it could be for six years.
So drawing on the American exemplar, as you say, they want the king to play the part that the British king plays and essentially the British king.
With the, the glorious revolution hanging over his or her head, the, the sense that a king who doesn't play his part can be kicked out.
The British king has the power of veto over all legislation, but essentially is very, very reticent in using it.
Yeah.
And I think that is what they want.
They want someone who will have the power of veto because that will, as you say, it will kind of provide a check on what they would see as excesses of, of popular fervor, but at the same time, they need a king who will not be.
Too ready to use it.
And the question is, is Louis the 16th qualified to play that role?
So that's one issue, but the other issue facing the monachia as they come to be called the monarchists is, um, the fact that there are lots of radical deputies in the assembly who view any prospect of the king having any kind of veto as an absolute outrage.
Yeah.
And there are a lot aren't there who, one difference between the, the, the, as it were the British revolution, if you want to call it that.
Which nobody ever does.
And the French revolution is in Britain that the idea of the separation of powers as in the United States is seen as incredibly healthy and organic and, and, you know, necessary check and a balance.
But in France, you now have this sort of romantic fervor and the idea of la nation and the assembly reflects in the general will of the nation.
So there are lots of people who say, well, why would we divide it up?
And we've just done away with different orders.
Yeah.
So the three estates have all been swallowed up into the national assembly.
Exactly.
So why then, because essentially the, you know, if you're having a Senate of the great and the good, that means bishops, it means aristocrats.
Um, so you, you can understand the, the suspicion.
Um, so the Abbe Dessier who, who we met, um, in, uh, early on in the, the, the kind of the debate around the, the, um, the three estates Versailles, he describes the whole proposal as a letter de cachet launched against the national will against the
the entire nation.
Mm-hmm.
So comparing it to a kind of unjust monarchical repression of liberty.
And that idea of the national will quite a dangerous idea.
You might say in the long run.
Well, there also, but also the idea that sovereignty resides in, in the nation, which is, you know, one of the key principles of the, the declaration of rights.
Um, and if that is the case, then how can any individual, even the king stand against the sovereignty of the nation?
And you know, it's a, it's.
It's a real problem, and it results in the National Assembly essentially kind of splitting
into rival factions.
And what happens is that the monaciens, the enthusiasts for the kind of British-style
constitution start to congregate on the right side of the meeting hall, and their opponents,
those who want a more radical solution, on the left.
And Dominic, that's a division that we still see stamped on politics.
Yeah.
Left and right.
Absolutely.
To this very day.
But actually, they reach a kind of compromise, don't they?
So this is, what, September 1789?
They reject a second chamber.
That's decisively rejected, and the Constitutional Committee, which is full of all these kind
of metropolitan elite types, that gets dissolved.
So that's clearly a victory for the more radical wing.
But you're right.
Around the veto.
There is a kind of compromise that doesn't really satisfy anyone.
So the King is allowed a veto, but it's a suspensive one.
So it's a bit like the House of Lords in, what was it, 1910 or something?
It's great to get Asquith back on the show, and Asquith's Britain.
So yeah, the House of Lords can postpone legislation or sort of block it, but then basically the
Commons can break the logjam under the Parliament Act.
Yeah.
So the King can veto legislation three times, and then basically if they bring it back again-
Which I think effectively means two years.
Right.
So he has a two-year block on legislation.
Okay.
And then if they come back and say, no, we still want it, he then can't resist it.
Which actually, to me, seems quite a good, it's a safety valve, it's a cooling off period,
as it were.
But the right wing don't like it because it makes it impossible to preserve a kind of
genuine balance of powers.
Yeah.
So that's very important to them.
And it doesn't satisfy the radicals because the King can still frustrate the will of the
sovereign people.
Yeah.
So both sides are kind of cross.
But there's also, I think, by this point, a sense that what people in the National Assembly
think is not necessarily decisive because there is also the will of the people as expressed
by the inhabitants of Paris.
And in Paris, people don't understand the veto at all.
They kind of think it's a new tax, lots of them.
And even those who don't, they don't really know what it is, but they're against it.
That's the bottom line.
And this is driven, I think, by, first of all, a kind of growing sense of hostility
to the King personally.
And this is fostered by the fact that he has been notably silent about the repudiation
of feudalism and the declaration of rights.
And I think we said in the previous episode, and then on the 19th of September, he does
finally comment on this kind of repudiation of feudal rights, but he hedges it around
with so many qualifications that it ends up sounding like he's actually rejecting it.
And the deputies are very upset about this.
And in Paris, everyone is absolutely furious.
And then on the 4th of October, he voices reservations about the declaration of rights.
And I suppose the King would say, well, why shouldn't I, I'm the King, but in the context
of a liberty loving.
Of course people with sovereignty, you know, this is dangerous.
And I think also there is a sense in Paris that the national assembly itself is compromised
by its willingness to treat with the King and there's talk that they want to move it
to from, from Versailles and the Paris region to tour the city on the law, which is famously
Royalist and would kind of therefore get them out of the crosshairs of, of the, of Parisian
popular opinion.
And they're not in favor of that at all.
And the other thing that is happening in August and through into September, which everyone
knows is incredibly problematic, uh, both for those who are starving and those who have
to keep a lid on, um, things that are bubbling away in France is the fact that the price
of bread is starting to go up again.
So it had declined kind of in early August, but it's now going up.
Um, and this isn't because there's terrible weather.
The weather's very good.
The, the, the grain is ripening.
It's kind of.
Ready to be harvested.
But the problem is that the, um, the weather is so good that all the mills have been immobilized
because there's no water in the rivers.
So you start to get bread riots, you get demands for higher wages, and you get these familiar
accusations, which the Marquis de Sade makes such play with in his novels that the King
and the aristocracy are deliberately trying to starve the revolution to death.
So it's a useful reminder, isn't it?
That there are these two different dimensions to the revolution.
So on the one hand, there's the dimension of kind of.
Politics and ideas and everything that's going on in the national assembly as people
are moving into their different factions left and right.
And then outside, you know, none of that would have the salience and it wouldn't be so charged
were it not for the fact that outside there are people starving, there is a, there is
a real anger on the streets, isn't there?
And the danger, the huge danger for the, the authors of the revolution is that they have,
you know, maybe on what could they do about it?
But.
They have allowed people, they've given people the impression that changes to the political
and financial kind of structure will magically transform the situation on the streets and
mean that bread prices fall and all that kind of thing.
And actually a lot of them have known, you know, that they're, they're, they're as what
we would call neoliberals.
They have no intention of fixing the price of bread and, and helping people out and doing
all these kinds of things.
Yeah.
Because.
Because May's radical could be September's conservative.
Exactly.
And things are moving so fast.
So there's a sense that lots of deputies are kind of running very fast up a down escalator,
just trying to kind of avoid themselves being chewed up by, by, by, by the revolution.
And this is turbocharged by the fact, of course, that the declaration of rights has, has officially
abolished censorship.
And that means that there's basically nothing the authorities can do to restrain.
I mean, expressions of hostility, whether it's to the king or to the national assembly
or, or, or, or whoever.
And there is a particular newspaper which is launched on the 12th of September.
So against the backdrop of all these events, which really, really demonstrates how potent
journalism can now be.
And this is a paper, it's not its original name, but it's, it's, it's, it's ultimate
name is .
So the People's Friend.
And its editor is a man called Jean-Paul Marin, who is, he's basically, he's kind of drifted
from job to job.
He's someone who's never really held down a secure position.
He's he's a scientist, he's a physician, he's a political theorist actually for a while,
a bit like our gold hanger stablemate, Alan Shearer, Dominic.
Yeah.
He actually very similar.
He lived in Newcastle.
Very similar.
I've often thought that.
Except that, unlike Alan Shearer, unlike, I mean, Alan Shearer never became, ended up
physician to the, the bodyguard of the Comte d'Artois.
Alan Shearer also, I mean, I'll say you can say what you like about Alan Shearer, but
he's got lovely skin and Mara has terrible skin.
Mara does have absolutely terrible skin.
Yes.
And also he's, he's never written a paper on the gonorrhea of one of his friends.
As far as you know, Tom.
As far as I know.
You don't know about.
I don't know what he's been up to with Craig Bellamy or Les Ferdinand or any of his Newcastle
stablemates.
So anyway.
So Mara comes back from St. James's Park to Paris.
And he's kind of drifting around, he's a bit of a bum.
I mean, he's the classic example of the underpaid intellectual, the undervalued intellectual
is always the great driver of revolutions.
And Mara's the kind of classic example, and he finds in the revolution and the chance
to edit this paper.
Yeah.
So he's, he has some great experience with the people's friend.
Absolutely.
Everything that he's ever been made for, you know, it's completely his, his vacation.
And essentially he is brilliant at blaming everything on conspiracies, on plots, on attempts
by sinister figures to to destroy the people.
So he calls his enemies bloodsuckers very much into the kind of the language of vampirism.
And he's.
Wow.
deputies in the national assembly are trying to kind of sort the constitution out he's piling in
you know full full kind of angry person on twitter yeah so open your eyes shake off your lethargy
purge your committees preserve only the healthy members sweep away the corrupt the royal pensioners
and the devious aristocrats intrigues and false patriots you have nothing to expect from them
except servitude poverty and desolation mara is such a he's such a familiar figure because he's
that he's that person who suddenly sees he's been a loser basically in a drifter as you said
and he's suddenly in the chaos of the revolution sees his opportunity to make a name for himself by
this this unbelievably ferocious invective i mean we do see people like it today don't we
um well you so so there's a sense in which this is alien i think it's not too uh too much of an
anachronism to call them centrists people who
who initially had been in favor of the revolution and now with this kind of ever more radical
language are starting to think oh hold on so often these are foreign foreign admirers of the
revolution so there's there's an english visitor uh in paris who'd come there because he was kind
of so excited by what was going on who is is following these kind of attacks on the national
assembly and he's he writes woe woe be to the legislature that employs a senseless profligate
rabble to enforce its laws lanterns are
monuments in this country so lanterns you slinger a rope over it and hang your enemies yeah lynching
basically basically lynching yes and so there you have opposed senses of where sovereignty should lie
is does the people sovereignty lie on the streets or does it lie in kind of constitutional forms and
this is the great question that the revolution is kind of focusing and it it results in a kind of
as in
july early july so in september get moving into october a kind of a sense of potential violence
in the capital directed now not just against the royal family but also against the national
assembly both of whom of course are in versailles and even in august you had had a kind of an
aristocrat who'd been imprisoned in in charenton where the marquis de sade had been sent and the
kind of the sardian quality of quite a lot of this is is i just don't know i don't know i don't know
it's quite fascinating but anyway so he this was a marquee and he had proposed a march on versailles
um and and that had kind of fizzled out but in the palais royal which is this kind of great center of
free speech owned by the um by the duke of orleans the cousin of of louis the 16th lots of radical
circles are saying we should organize a coup we should march on versailles you know we should get
the royal family um and essentially the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the
the city feels that it is poised between further expressions of of revolutionary fervor or
counter-revolution yeah and you know this is for those who are who are in charge of of keeping the
city basically you know stopping riots breaking out this is a nightmare because how do you stop
well this is the question right why don't the authorities i mean they have they have money
they have armed men why don't they in some way clamp down and try and police this
well for starters as you said there's the the issue around censorship they can't control what
is now being said so as in uh the the 1650s in england revolution has bred freedom of speech
which in turn fosters further revolutionary activity so that's that's one part of it but
the other thing is is that if you were saying that the structures of power are feudal and
expressions of a kind of blood-sucking vampirism very difficult very difficult to take charge of
so all of those have been erased the bastille has gone the literature cachet has gone all of that
so essentially in a very kind of orwellian step the revolutionaries find that they have to
resurrect what they have yeah eliminated it's interesting they're doing this so early right
in 1789 so within just a few couple of months really of the fall of the bastille at the end
of that summer the in the autumn they're already thinking we have to bring back um what do they
call it the search committee
so they're opening letters and doing all that kind of thing yeah so sharma in in his in citizens
describes it as the first organ of a revolutionary police state and essentially it it it takes for
itself all the powers of of the of the ancien regime that everyone had condemned so um you know
they can open letters they can uh sponsor spies they can um search houses without warrants
amazingly they can even imprison people who are suspected of being in danger to the revolution
yeah so it's basically the whole electric cachet system um so that's one aspect of it you've got
kind of the development of a kind of proto-secret police but you also have the national guard of
course that we talked about before uh commanded by lafayette and it's his job essentially to
maintain order in the capital but he's finding an increasing struggle because he's you know he's
he's about 10 he's got all these terror i mean basically he's you know he's coping with a
situation that no one has ever had to cope with before well you and i thought we were talking about
disagree about lafayette don't we i think if he had been you know a man of greater cold-blooded
ruthlessness he could have seized this opportunity and really made a name for himself but he's a bit
of a diddler do you think it's fair to say he feels himself caught between different i look on
him much more favorably i think that he is i mean he's an enthusiast for the revolution he's you
know he's not a counter-revolutionary and he is struggling with a situation that that no one has
really ever had to face before well actually see what tom somebody has faced this before and later
on as we will see in this in this episode yes okay so people compare him with an english predecessor
and if he had been if he'd had anything like the backbone and the spirit of that english predecessor
he'd one day have been lord protector of france but it wasn't to be possibly yeah possibly um
anyway so september turns to october capital's getting ever more ready to kind of blow up
price of bread is going up and then
on the 2nd of october details of a scandal in versailles arrives in paris and again and again
we've been talking about how important the details of royal scandals are in affecting the course of
events and this is seen as an absolute shocker so mariah is all over it you know the uh the people's
friend he loves this and the story goes that um the king has summoned a regiment from the northeast
frontier the flanders regiment they've
arrived in versailles and his bodyguard have um staged a banquet for them and staging a banquet
at a time when people in paris are starving is seen as being very offensive anyway but
this banquet is supposed to have degenerated into an orgy
sponsored by the queen yeah and most shockingly of all um all the the participants in this banquet
are supposed to have taken the revolutionary cascade so the um the tricolor and trampled it
underfoot and the queen is said to have approved of it all and in in paris this is seen as a kind of
blasphemy and it it turbo charges all the old rumors that the queen you know of her depravity
of her her kind of empiric qualities her desire to starve the poor of of paris to death but it
combines two different conspiracy theories really doesn't it one is the thing about marianne's own
energy mentioned but the other is all through the summer and the autumn people have been
anxious about the arrival of troops from the frontiers yeah german-speaking troops in
particular so the flanders regiment for these the idea that these people have turned up they're
going to be the vanguard of the counter-revolution they're in league with the bloodsuckers
in the court i mean it could not be a better gift to somebody like mara
yeah and and it spreads terror through it throughout the kind of the poorest quarters
in paris on the morning of the 5th of october very early um a market woman she stands up
as she addresses all the other women who have started gathering for the for the day's market
and she harangues them saying that the fact that they can't afford to get bread that they can't
afford to put food on their family's tables that this is due to the queen due to the vampires of
versailles and they should march on the palace and well who knows what but what happens dominic will
change the face
of the world
france forever what drama tom so that morning uh marie antoinette is in um her little model
village the petty tree and all um she's been feeding her ducks feeding her goldfish um and
then she's she's been left a bit tired by this and so she retires to a grotto for a little rest
oh that's nice um her husband the king has been out shooting um normally he would have gone hunting
but he is aware that trouble is brewing in paris and so um by going shooting it means that he can
be it's easy to to contact him should developments happen and he has a very successful day shooting
and in his his journal he notes killed 81 head a poor show by the standards of franz ferdinand
and george the fifth by the standards absolutely but i think not bad for a morning yeah that's the
difference between the austrians and the french isn't it the austrians are so ruthless
yeah well that's certainly what
the
mobs in paris would say when they talk about marie antoinette um and of course both both of
these activities are absolutely calculated to infuriate virtuous patriots because marie
antoinette playing with her animals in the petty tree and all i mean this will become
in a way the defining image of her the the kind of the role playing the scene is fabulous i mean
we talked about how i think marie antoinette is sees it as an expression of her sympathy with the
poor but this is not how the poor themselves see it and the the king going shooting again this is
a kind of deliberately offensive because as one of the um the feudal um privileges that have been
jettisoned is the right that the nobility had to um to go shooting um and so with the the abolition
of the feudal monopolies on on hunting and shooting basically every bird in france has
been wiped out so you may complain that the king hasn't been shooting enough but it's not the case
birds but i mean all over france it's just bang bang bang and um our old friend arthur young the
uh the englishman who's been traveling across france and whose journalists we've been drawing
a lot for this series he he's in provence when um suddenly it becomes legal for for everyone to go
out shooting and he says i would i i've been pestered with all the mob of the country shooting
one would think that every rusty gun in provence is at work killing all sorts of birds the shot
has fallen five or six times in my chase and about my ears so that's something that
hasn't changed really in france that's still very much going on but you know dominic this is the last
time the king will have the option of choosing whether to go shooting or hunting what a sad day
will be the last time that the queen will get to feed her ducks the ducks and the real losers and
all this aren't they they probably end up being eaten by son culotte i imagine they'll be shot
yeah yes so um as louis notes in his journal um interrupted by events and that of course is his
own so ten o'clock in the morning um marianne trinette is is uh reposing in her grotto when
um she is informed that an armed force has left paris and is marching on versailles and brilliantly
she's informed by her hairdresser is that right mr leonard who is the the sort of the
metrosexual friend of marianne trinette isn't he yes well that's what he's that's what he later
says it has to be said that this is uncorroborated by anyone else right but but yes he he yes
absolutely coming to the coming to the rescue of his his diva friend um more tricky to trickier to
get in touch with with lou the 16th because he's out shooting but you know they find him and he is
back by three o'clock in the afternoon and there's a meeting of the royal council and they don't know
what to do and there is discussion that perhaps the king and queen should i don't know head for
the frontier head for somewhere secure but what's fascinating is that even at this stage the king is
in court politics because he blames the duke of orleans who owns the you know the palo real where
all these uh kind of radicals uh a meeting and he it's as though he still quite hasn't got
the hang of the fact that this is no longer about dukes conspiring about their cut against their
customers but about something much profound but here's the interesting thing I guess he is so
ill-traveled he's only ever been out of the versailles kind of bubble really twice hasn't he
um he went
out for his coronation and he went to Cherbourg to inspect some defenses so he's he's very you
know poorly I mean he's been to his palace in in Paris the Tuileries but he doesn't have any sense
of what is going on so how could he understand I guess the anger on the streets and all of that
kind of thing would take a profound political imagination to grasp that and he is a very
unimaginative man and and Marie Antoinette I think is the same that for her crowds are a
kind of background for the display of her own magnificence
and she simply has no comprehension of what they might be feeling what the kind of the individual
components of those crowds might might be like so for both of them it's really difficult and even for
the members of the National Assembly they don't know what is coming they're not sure what to expect
when you know who who is long who is coming from Paris why what do they want uh and it takes time
for them to kind of properly appreciate what's going on so to that question that you know who is
There are basically three groups of people.
So there is the market women of Paris, the fishwives, and there it's been escalating
very quickly since the one woman stood up and said, we should march on Versailles.
One of the women gets hold of a drum and she starts beating it.
And then they get the bells of a nearby church to start ringing.
So it kind of talks in ringing out huge crowd forms.
They start to march on the Hotel de Ville.
They are chanting the title of a particularly popular pamphlet, When Will We Have Bread?
They start reaching for cudgels, for sticks, for knives, any kind of weapon that they can
get.
By the time these various groups converge on the Hotel de Ville, there are about six
or 7,000 of them, and they absolutely ransack it, seizing it for muskets, for rifles, for
weapons.
Whatever they can get, they even find two cannon.
So this is again, kind of quite like the Bastille, a huge mob looking for weapons.
By this point, it is pouring down with rain and normally rain is what stops revolutions,
but not in this case.
Despite the rain, the women with their two cannon and all their weapons and their cudgels
and things start heading off for Versailles.
Can I just interrupt at this point, Tom?
So the interesting thing about them heading to Versailles is these women, the sort of
fishwives, market women.
They were known as poissard.
And they would go to Versailles every year anyway.
They used to go to Versailles on the 25th of August, the feast of Saint Louis, and they
would give flowers to the queen.
So it was a kind of ritual.
And so she was used to seeing them and she actually, you know, you were saying about
the thing with the and pretending, feeding the ducks and pretending, you know,
to be an ordinary farm girl and stuff.
They would do plays and stuff at the Versailles where they would affect the dialect of the
fishwives.
And they would use that.
And these were very common in France, you know, the fishwives were, they were stock
figures.
They were laughing stock, I guess.
And Marie Antoinette herself had kind of got people to try and teach her their lingo and
stuff.
So there is a dreadful irony at the back of all this.
There is.
And that is exactly the tension between Marie Antoinette's understanding of what a crowd
should be and what a crowd might actually be.
Yeah.
And that's part of what makes it the whole experience that is coming so completely traumatic
for her.
And I don't think there's any ambivalence in the attitude of the women towards the queen.
I think they are pretty universally hostile to her for all the reasons that we've been
discussing.
Attitudes to Louis is a slightly more ambivalent.
So they're calling him Le Bon Papa, the good father, and they want him to give them bread.
And it's unclear whether they are.
Oh, oh.
They are calling him Le Bon Papa out of hostility, kind of sense of irony, or whether they genuinely
mean it.
And it may be that there's a kind of a gray area where they can't quite decide whether
he is the enemy or their friend.
But definitely they are also saying that if he is Le Bon Papa, he should be with his children
in Paris, not stuck out in Versailles.
And this increasingly becomes part of what they're talking about as they head out to
the palace.
Yeah.
And as they go, they start picking up large numbers of men as well.
And on their way, they meet with a contingent of the Flanders regiment.
And they're nervous about this because the Flanders regiment is seen as the great defenders
of the monarchy.
But the Flanders regiment, they're all in favor of it.
These are the people who have been accused of trampling the Cacade, but actually they
turn out to be great enthusiasts for the revolution.
And they greet the marchers and they say, brilliant, we're with you.
Hooray.
Let's get, let's crack onto Versailles.
And this is an expression of a familiar problem that the king can't trust his own troops.
Because troops are people too.
Without troops.
They're hungry.
Yeah.
They're impatient with authority.
And they're like, yeah, why not?
Actually, this is great.
This is great fun.
Let's all go to Versailles.
You know, and troops have been disobeying their officers since the very beginning of the revolution
for months.
Yeah.
And I think the fact that it is fun, you know, if you, if you have subject to kind of brutal
discipline as dragoons are, or if you're, you know, you're starving.
And hungry and you can't feed your children as so many of the women are quite aside from
anything else, the chance to have a kind of expedition to Versailles, even if it's pissing
down with rain is, I mean, it, it, it's, it's something exciting.
It's so important in all revolutions and riots, actually, Tom, and something that I think
historians sometimes underplay is, is exactly this point that one of the key things I always
think in the momentum of any uprising, any rebellion, any riot is that the sense of the
carnivalesque, I guess, of it being a tremendous laugh and actually, yeah, let's go for it.
And the momentum and the giddiness of it all, and you really get that sense, don't you?
The closer they get to Versailles, more and more people are joining them because this
is a tremendous occasion and I can't, I don't want to, who knows what's going to happen.
Let's, let's pile in kind of all this more women.
There's a woman who looks amazing on a kind of, what's her name, who's the kind of Amazon.
Yeah.
So the, the Amazon, which is, and again, there's a kind of sense of cosplay there.
I think that, you know, she, she's wearing a plumed hat.
She's got a red riding coat.
She's got loads of pistols in her belt.
She's got swords.
She's cuts a tremendous dash on her horse and, and she will always be kind of remembered
as the, the kind of the, the emblematic figure of this march of the women, even though she
is not a fishwife.
I mean, she, you know, she's got a horse for starters.
But the sense that there is a slightly carbon carnivalesque quality to what is happening.
Yeah.
And if it, I think that if it was just the, if it was just the women marching and even,
you know, the, the members of the Flanders regiment, it wouldn't be quite as alarming
as it turns out to be for the national assembly and for the king, because the other group
of people who end up marching on Versailles is the, the national guard.
So under Lafayette, who was supposed to be keeping order in Paris, and they are marching
on Versailles five hours behind the market women.
Yeah.
What Lafayette's doing.
He's basically appalled that his men want to go out and join the women on the march
on Versailles, because he immediately understands that this is a altogether different quality
of insurrection to a bunch of fishwives going out to Paris to have the, the, the officially
mandated guard in Paris do that.
I mean, that is, I know very, very kind of menacing revolutionary activity, an expression
of hostility to the constitution and to the monarchy, which Lafayette is sufficiently a
centrist dad, not to want to be involved in.
Um, but it basically has, he has very little choice because I think he has the feeling
that if he doesn't go along with his men, they leave the dessert or, or murder him or
nothing good will come of it.
So rather than morosely, he gets onto his horse and kind of rides out of their head.
It's still driving rain.
He's got 15,000 of the guard behind him.
So that's an enormous number of people.
And he heads off, uh, and one witness describes him as the prisoner of his own troops, which
effectively is what he is.
So you now have two groups of people.
You have the, the, the, the women and you have the national guard, both descending on
Paris.
So the women arrive first, they try and break into, uh, the, the, the palace of Versailles
itself, but the King's bodyguards and the Swiss guard turned them back.
So then they march on the national assembly and they invade it and they demand to see
the king.
There are amazing descriptions of them in the national assembly by the way, because
they're so, they're sodden and they're kind of, they're literally like steaming as they
come in and they're, and they're, and you said the metropolitan elite kind of delegates,
which basically they all are, they're all lawyers and stuff, aren't they, are sitting
there kind of incredibly awkward and frightened, I think, and disturbed a lot of them as this
great mob of people charge breaks into the assembly and people start like they start
messing around with the debt deputies stuff and all that kind of chatter.
Yeah.
And they're kind of just, I mean, they're like a kind of walking pub, you know, walking
holiday in the late district, they've all kind of burst in absolutely drenched and steaming.
Um, so the deputies send a messenger to the king who's back now and they say, look, would
you receive a delegation of the women?
And he's, he says, yes, of course.
So the women choose the perfect person to speak to him, which is a 17 year old flower
girl called Pierrette Chabris, who is, um, she's very shy.
Um, very pretty.
Very virtuous looking, which is, you know, very important.
She doesn't speak like a fishwife.
She is renowned for her, her kind of genteel language.
Um, so she has chosen the spokeswoman.
She goes forward.
She looks at the king and she's so overwhelmed that she faints and the king then fetches
her smelling salts, um, helps her to her feet.
It's all tremendous PR.
Um, he then explains to the women that he, um, he's given orders for any grain that has
been held up on the roads leading into Paris.
Yeah.
He delivered as a matter of absolute urgency that he'll do his best to source them more
grain and the women are kind of mollified.
But Louis knows even so that, you know, he is staring down a barrel here.
And so that evening, unsurprisingly, he finally accepts both the abolition of feudalism and
the declaration of rights, um, without any qualification whatsoever.
And it is said that as he, as he, you know, he signs his approval, he does so with tears
in his eyes.
But Tom, this is just the first group because, uh, 15,000 men are also on their way.
Um, and they're not really, I mean, Lafayette is now basically their trophy rather than
their commander.
Um, and, and they are a much more terrifying prospect than the market women are, aren't
they?
They are.
And they are absolutely set on bringing the king and queen back.
And when Lafayette arrives, he goes to the national assembly.
He explains this to them.
Um, and he then demands.
An audience with the king who has retreated to the palace and the king sends a messenger
out and says, yeah, you can come in, but you have to, you know, you have to be unarmed
and Lafayette agrees to this.
And so, um, a courtier comes that, you know, Chamberlain comes and gets him and he is led
into the palace and dominate.
You referenced this in the end of the first half, as he goes in a courtier sees Lafayette
walking into the palace and says, there goes all of a Cromwell and Lafayette turns around
and says, Cromwell.
That would not have come unarmed.
You may feel that that proves what you're saying.
I think it's worth just stopping a second.
Lafayette does have a tremendous opportunity here.
He is a hero of the American war.
He is arguably one of the two or three most famous men in France.
He has under his command, you know, tens of thousands of men, potentially a different
man, a Napoleon or a Cromwell could have turned that into a power base, a really ruthless,
hard nosed political operator.
I think it's to his credit that he doesn't.
Of course you do.
Of course you think that.
But I mean, I don't.
I think he's, I think, I think that he's, he's, um, he's a centrist dad and he is trying to
ensure that the centre holds and he's doing his best, but we know that that is not going
to succeed.
But I think it's to his credit that he, he kind of, as it were, sticks to his guns, even
though he will end up with not many guns by the end of the day.
He doesn't stick to his guns.
You know, there's other people take them.
And anyway, listen, tell us what happens when he gets in to see the King.
Okay.
So he, like the women is, you know, he's drenched, he's spattered with mud.
He's an absolute picture.
Um, he comes into the, into, into Louie's presence and takes off his hat, sweeps all
this kind of thing.
And he, he, he, he declares in ringing tones, I have come to die at the feet of your majesty,
obviously pre-prepared again, I imagine that this will confirm you in your sense of contempt
for him.
I like it.
I like a man.
He prepares a melodramatic statement.
No, I mean, you've got to prepare.
I think it's a good statement, but, but I, anyway, go on.
Yeah.
I think it's a good statement.
Anyway.
So, so, so, so he, so Lafayette then kind of reiterates to the King, look, you've got
to get as much grain to the capital as you possibly can.
And your majesty, I'm afraid that you have to come with, with me and the national guard
back to Paris.
You know, the national guard are not going to have it any other way.
Louie agrees to the first request.
I mean, he's, you know, he's already given orders that all the grain that can possibly
be found, be sent to Paris as soon as possible, but he does stonewall the second.
And he says, look, I'm going to have to consult with the queen and Mary Antoinette has already
gone to bed.
So we'll have to be left to the morning.
So the King goes to bed about two o'clock Lafayette stays there.
He wants to make sure that there's not going to be any trouble, but by about five o'clock
he fails.
Okay.
So the night's passed.
It's just before dawn.
I could probably go and grab a few, a few winks.
So he is married to a member of the Nye family, you remember, so he, they have a big house
in Versailles.
So he goes off there.
And he finds a sofa and curls up and has a sleep.
And that is, that is, I mean, that is Lafayette's fatigue, right?
That is absolutely textbook again.
I I'm in Versailles with a huge mob, a huge mob of fish, fish wives.
I've also got 15,000 men.
I've got 15,000 men who are kind of totally out of control.
I think I'll just go for a little nap now and have a lie down.
What could go wrong?
As a man who likes to sleep.
I have nothing but sympathy.
But you are right that this, this, this doesn't, it turns out not to be being a brilliant move
because about half an hour after Lafayette has gone, it's dawn, so kind of misty morning,
a portion of the crowd, which is kind of intermingled fish wives and, uh, soldiers of the national
guard finally break into the Royal palace.
And first thing they say is where are the apartments of the queen?
You know, we, we hate the queen.
Um.
And they're saying that we, we want to make a cocaine.
Out of her intestines and others are saying, we want to decapitate her.
Uh, we want to fry up her heart and liver, eat them, uh, and.
We want to do even worse.
What's worse.
It's obviously who knows, who knows anyway.
So this is very bad news for Mary Antoinette.
So they descend on the, uh, on the queen's apartments.
There are two bodyguards standing outside.
They get cut down, killed, decapitated.
These are the heads that will have died.
They appear on the pikes that are mentioned in, in, in the, the reading that you, we began
this episode with.
There's a third bodyguard.
He manages to alert a lady in waiting, who rushes off to, to, to, to wake up the queen.
He is then cut down and left for dead, although amazingly, actually he, he survives.
Mary Antoinette meanwhile has, you know, she's been gone out of bed.
She's barefoot, um, and it seems like she's stuck in her apartment, but amazingly and
fortuitously for her way back in 1775, she had ordered the construction of a.
From a secret tunnel that would go from her appointments to the king's appointments because
she was, uh, this was a time when she was anxious to establish her, you know, her influence
over, over Louis.
And so she is able to use that and the, the, the, the passageway is kind of concealed in
the paneling.
So it shuts behind her and she goes rushing off, um, as she reaches the king's quarters,
knocks on the door.
And there's no, and she's in her night and she's barefoot and she's sobbing with terror.
Yeah.
And the most unbelievable scene.
Yes.
And, and meanwhile, back in her bedroom, the, the, the, the people who've broken in, uh,
absolutely infuriated that she's not there.
And so they start slashing at her, her, her mattress, um, with their swords and all the
while Mary Antoinette is hammering on the door saying, please, please let me in.
And finally someone hears and opens the door and she gets it.
She, she, she stumbles in.
And it said that, that the terror of this experience is so great that her hair, which
previously had been.
Blonde from this point on, you know, the, the bottoms go white.
So, so a couple of things on this one is you described that scene of the, the two bodyguards
being, you know, we sort of threw in a way, we just sort of went through that in a sentence,
but that is a horrendous scene, right?
They are, I mean, a mob basically grabbing these two guys, hacking them to death with
knives and then sawing off their heads with the knives.
I mean, again, a really horrific scene.
And so I think it could absolutely have, have spiraled hideously out of control.
If they'd got Mary Antoinette, she'd be dead.
There's no question.
There's no question about that.
Do you not think?
Oh, completely.
I mean, they would have lynched her.
They would have made cockades out of her.
They would have butchered her.
And I remember when I was a boy seeing a documentary about the French revolution, sort of dramatized
documentary or something like that.
And this scene was at the center of it.
And you could argue this scene is in a way the center of, dare I say, the conservative
imagination, the idea of an out, you know, it's a classic trope, isn't it?
The out of control mob.
And the, the woman.
The woman in tears fleeing for her life.
And they are going to butcher her.
I mean, that's, that's very Burkean, I guess that, that image, isn't it?
It is.
Yes, it, it absolutely is, which is why he situates Mary Antoinette in the way he does
in his Jeremiah against the revolution.
But it, it, it doesn't explode in that way.
She doesn't end up dead.
She is reunited with Louis.
And again, I think a lot of the credit for this can be given to Lafayette who has been
alerted.
Who's been asleep.
Yeah.
He's, he's smashed half an hour of sleep, Dominic.
He's woken up.
He doesn't go, oh, leave me alone.
I need to catch up on my sleep.
Oh, what a hero.
He comes rushing out.
What a great man.
And he comes into the, comes into the courtyard and he sees these heads of the Royal Bodyguards
on sticks kind of bobbing around.
And he calms everybody down.
I mean, he manages to, to say, you know, guys, just, you know, chill.
You've done him as Tony Blair there.
And then he goes, guys, you know, hey, we're, we're the people's bodyguard.
And then he goes, you know, you've done him as Tony Blair there.
And then he goes in and is very Tony Blair and the Queen.
And he, he, he tells the King and Queen, look, we've got to calm the situation down.
And Louis is saying, you know, we, we, all this stuff about, you know, the guard trampling
on the cockade.
It never happened.
And Lafayette says, yeah, fine.
Okay.
Listen.
So what we've got to do is you've got to go out on the balcony and you have got to address
the people outside.
I've done my best to calm them down, but ultimately it's best coming from you.
So Louis then goes out onto the balcony and he addresses the crowd.
And he says, yes, I will come with you to Paris.
Again, he, he insists that his bodyguards are innocent, that they hadn't trampled on
the cockade and Lafayette is with him.
And you know, he's very, very good at the PR.
What he does is he takes a tricolour cockade and he embraces an officer of the bodyguard
and he pins the cockade to the bodyguard's hat.
And by doing that, he's essentially folding the bodyguard into the warm embrace of the
revolution.
I think that's.
I mean, you may say it's very Tony Blair.
I don't necessarily see that as a criticism, but I think he's done for, I think he's done
very well.
In a horrific situation, which could easily have ended with the King, the Queen and Lafayette
himself being butchered with, you know, kitchen knives.
He's actually, he's actually played, I mean, apart, the falling asleep, I think is madness,
but actually the stuff with the cockade is a brilliant bit of political theatre and there's
more to come, isn't there, with the Queen?
Well, there is.
There is, because there is still the question of the Queen, who the mob will hate.
And so Lafayette says, look, you've got to go out onto the balcony as well.
And she's terrified.
I mean, entirely understandably, she's heard what they were shouting about her.
So but Lafayette says, no, you must.
And so she goes out onto the balcony with her children, but the people out in the courtyard
start baying at this and saying she has to stand there alone.
So she sends the children back in, she steps out onto the balcony facing the crowd who
only, you know.
Half an hour before we're wanting to rip out her intestines.
And again, Lafayette joins her and he bows low before her and he kisses her hand.
And there's a kind of silence and it's not clear what the reaction of the crowd is going
to be.
And then they start shouting, vive la reine, long live the Queen.
And again, Lafayette has kind of ridden the wave of emotion and turned it, turned the
tide.
And so Marie Antoinette goes back.
But of course she's still completely traumatized.
And I think she sees perhaps even more clearly than Louis, just the, you know, the, the scale
of the horrors that clearly now face them.
So she goes back in and she tells, she speaks to a lady in waiting and she says, they want
to force us, the King and me to go to Paris with the heads of our bodyguards carried before
us at the end of their pikes.
And this is exactly what happens.
And it takes them seven hours to, to travel in their carriage from Versailles to Paris.
The whole way, Louis doesn't utter a single word.
You have as people kind of shouting slogans and gesticulating the Queen as, as the carriage
rides along.
Behind the, the, the Royal carriage, there are wagons loaded with all the, the flour
that had been taken from the, the stores at Versailles.
And on their arrival in Paris, they're forced to appear again on a balcony this time at
the Hotel de Ville.
And then finally by 8 PM.
They are able to leave.
They are able to kind of collapse into the palace has been allocated to them, the Tuileries.
And unbelievably, the person who is there to greet them is Axel von Fersen, the dashing
Swedish diplomat who everyone thinks has been having an affair with Marie Antoinette.
I mean, it's just madness that he, he he's, he's there.
And so, you know, an aide, an aide to the Queen says, get out of here.
You know, you're going to be torn to pieces.
If people find you here.
So he does that it they're obviously very, very depressed and that no one is more depressed
than the Dauphin who complains that his room is very ugly.
Although it has to be said he will come to no worse, Dominic.
Yeah.
So it's, so there we have it.
I mean, I mean, it's interesting, isn't it?
I wonder whether what listeners will make of this because some listeners might well
say, well, this is terribly biased.
You know, they, they, I don't feel sorry for them at all.
They're pampered and privileged and all that kind of thing.
They're living in the Gilded Splendour of Versailles when people are hungry, they had
it coming, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Personally, I think on a human level, especially Marie Antoinette and the misogyny directed
at her, I think it's quite hard to take that view.
I, I agree.
I mean, it's, it's a terrible ordeal and I think a terrible story, but to counterpoint
that, we, we don't have, you know, what we haven't given in this account is, you know,
the narrative of a woman whose children are starving today.
Of course.
Yeah.
No, I totally agree with you.
So that is the counterpoint to it.
So I think there's always, you know, the story of the great and the glamorous, because we
know the details always kind of blaze more brightly.
We don't have the account of someone who has been driven by despair to march on Versailles
and that is the counterpoint.
French, French people always say the British in particular love the story, love telling
the story from Burke onwards, Carlisle, Dickens, they love to tell the story through the eyes,
you know, with a sense of horror.
Fascinated horror at the revolution.
And they, they particularly through the eyes of the great and the good and Marie Antoinette
more than anybody.
And they kind of, when you mentioned in the very first episode in the series, the Kirsten
Dunst film, and when that came out, French critics said, oh, typical Anglo-Saxons.
They always tell the story through the eyes of Marie Antoinette and Theo, a producer who
pretends to be French, he's written in the chat, they're not wrong.
They are wrong, Theo.
That's why that's, you know, we're, we're the bosses here.
I can't believe that Theo is now choosing this, Tom, as an opportunity to flex his own
muscles.
What's that going to be?
A march on Chipping Norton?
I mean, I think the French revolution is a great and still enduringly controversial
subject because there is scope for both sides to be right and all indeed wrong.
And that sense of a division in the national assembly that we talked about between the
right and the left.
I mean, this.
Still.
It still structures attitudes to the revolution to this day.
And we can see that now, but of course, in the aftermath of the transportation of the
king and queen from Versailles to the Tuileries, there are still two obvious problems that
have not been solved.
And in fact, that the bringing of the king and queen to Paris in a way has only made
more glaring.
So firstly, how is the monarchy to be squared with the revolution?
And in the wake of the October days, as they're called.
All the events we've been describing, there's a determined effort on behalf of the constitutional
committee and the national assembly to remove any prospect of despotism as they see it coming
back.
So the king loses all his rights to propose laws.
It's decreed that his income will be determined by a vote in the national assembly.
He has to allow that his ministers will be impeached if it is judged that they're betraying
the revolution.
So essentially all the kind of the struts upholding his power have been completely knocked away.
And the question is, how will Louis adapt to this?
How will he cope with being kind of neutered in this way, becoming a mere constitutional
cipher?
So that's an open question.
But the other open question is, will the national assembly be able to preserve its role as the
voice of the nation?
Because it has been upstaged just as the king and queen have been upstaged.
Well, the national assembly thought sovereignty lies with us.
It now appears that sovereignty lies with these crowds on the streets of Paris.
With the people.
So it's uncertain.
It's unsurprising that in mid-October, the national assembly follows the king and queen
from Versailles to Paris.
And they are living with the consciousness of two massive risks.
The first is that they will fragment into factions, as has already begun to happen,
the fragmenting into left and right.
But also the ongoing risk of interventions from people who are not part of the assembly.
And with the concurrent risk of violence.
The threat of violence.
The threat of what will happen to the deputies if they do not legislate in accordance with
the wishes of the people is now a Damocles sword hanging over every deputy in the national
assembly.
A sword of Damocles.
I love it.
It's great to have a sword of Damocles on the pocket.
It's a sword of Damocles.
So we've had the storm clouds of revolution, and now we have the sword of Damocles.
And this is a development that is obviously very, very pregnant with implications for
the future.
So back in Versailles, some of the more radical deputies had joined a club that had originally
been set up by the deputies from Brittany.
And now they've moved to Paris.
They are looking for a new place to meet.
So they rent a meeting room that is conveniently located near the new hall where the national
assembly are meeting.
And initially membership of this club is limited to deputies.
But as the months go by, it starts to be opened up to ordinary citizens.
I mean, citizens, they have to pay a membership fee.
But otherwise, they can all kind of join.
And this club, they call themselves Les Amis de la Constitution, the Friends of the Constitution.
But increasingly, Dominic, they come to be known by another name.
And it's a name that derives from the fact that they have rented their meeting room from
the order of the Dominicans.
And in Paris, the Dominicans have a very distinctive nickname.
And it derives from the fact that the very first Dominican monastery in Paris, way back
in the Middle Ages, had been on the Rue Saint-Jacques.
And so they come to be called Jacobins.
And this is the nickname that comes to be given to the most radical of the clubs in
Paris.
And the existence of the Jacobins, as events will prove, spells nothing good for the royal
family.
Well, you know what Ben Kenobi said about the Jacobin club, Tom?
You will never find a more wretched high.
You will find the same high and the same grave of scum and villainy.
And on that bombshell, thank you so much for this terrifying story, or inspirational story
if you're Theo Young-Smith, our producer.
But Tom, merci beaucoup et au revoir.
Au revoir.